Dan Rosen

SUMMARY

Software engineer seeking a new career as a high school teacher. In over 18 years in the software industry, the times when I've most strongly felt I'd done something of real value were those when I helped people learn. I've been lucky to find occasional teaching opportunities through my work — either as an instructor, a mentor, a manager or even as a peer — but I believe I can have a much greater positive impact and more personal satisfaction by committing myself to public education.

SKILLS

Programming languages & tools: Java (Eclipse, Maven, JUnit), JavaScript (Node.js), Scala, Haskell, C/C++.

Teaching: curriculum development, presentation (live and recorded), hands-on pedagogy, individual mentoring.

LICENSURE

Mathematics (8-12): Provisional license (#505392), issued 06.28.2018

CAREER

Cimpress · Architect / Squad Lead. Waltham, MA

03.2017 - Present

Managed a team of five engineers responsible for authentication and authorization protocols. Gave frequent customer presentations, both prepared and impromptu, about the systems we support. Led group problem-solving and brainstorming discussions to build team understanding and consensus.

Twitter · Tech Lead / Engineering Manager. San Francisco, CA

04.2013 - 10.2015

Managed three teams responsible for Twitter's REST API, including auth, rate-limiting and Scala frameworks. Developed "Scala School" course and taught to all engineers in new-hire onboarding.

Provided 1:1 coaching and performance management for 10 engineers ranging from interns to senior staff.

Mentored three aspiring junior engineers at Hackbright, a local developer bootcamp for women.

Facilitated debates about distributed systems, functional programming, dependency injection and testing. Presented on "Purely Functional Data Structures" at JavaOne 2013.

Marakana · Lead Instructor. San Francisco, CA

11.2011 - 04.2013

Taught and coached over 1,000 engineers in person and via LiveLessons (published by Addison-Wesley). Researched, developed and delivered new training courses on Scala, Hadoop and JAX-RS. Modernized Marakana's Java courses, including fundamentals, advanced concurrency and web development. Community events: organized the SF Scala meetup, and production of NEScala 2012 conference videos. Business development: spearheaded Scala training partnership with Typesafe (now Lightbend).

${\bf Atlassian \cdot Senior\ Software\ Engineer\ /\ Developer\ Advocate.\ San\ Francisco,\ CA}$

03.2010 - 08.2011

Wrote plugin development tutorials, documentation, presentations and blogs.

Maintained cross-product plugin SDK and built the "Developer" tab in the Universal Plugin Manager.

Designed and built plugin usage tracking dashboard for the Atlassian Plugin Exchange (now Marketplace).

Coverity · Senior Software Engineer / Sales Engineer. San Francisco, CA

09.2006 - 04.2009

Led training sessions on software quality, static analysis theory, reporting accuracy and other topics. Planned and executed technical strategy for major customers, closing over \$1.5 million in product sales. Designed and delivered Visual Studio and Eclipse IDE plugins, directing a team of offshore developers.

Cloudmark · Software Engineer. San Francisco, CA

08.2004 - 12.2005

Contributed to anti-spam product, including fingerprinting, virus detection and internationalization.

AOL Music · Technical Lead. San Francisco, CA

02.2003 - 12.2003

Led four-person client development team for AOL Music's internet radio services.

DoCoMo USA Laboratories · Research Engineer (Contract). San Jose, CA

04.2002 - 12.2002

Researched new programming models, and prepared all technical reports and patent applications for the team.

Netscape Communications / AOL · Software Engineer. Mountain View, CA

07.2000 - 09.2001

Represented Netscape to the W3C XSL group; contributed to XSL 1.0 and XPath 2.0 standards. Contributed to Mozilla's cross-platform UI toolkit and embedding API.

EDUCATION

Brown University · Providence, RI

09.1996 - 05.2000

Awarded Bachelor of Arts with Honors in Computer Science, May 2000. Received Senior Prize in Computer Science, funded by the William Gaston Premium Scholarship.

Newton North High School · Newton, MA

09.1991 - 05.1996

Member of Science Bowl and Olympiad competition teams that placed first in New England every year. Worked as teaching assistant for Italian language classes, and was awarded a scholarship from Sons of Italy.